# Giuseppe Attanasio

#### Ph.D. STUDENT · POLITECNICO DI TORINO

Corso Duca degli Abruzzi, 24, 10129, Torino, Italy

#### ■ giuseppe.attanasio@polito.it

☆ gattanasio.cc | ② g8a9 | ☐ giuseppe-attanasio

"Computers aren't the thing. They are the thing that gets us to the thing." - Halt And Catch Fire

### Bio\_

I'm a second-year Ph.D. student at the Department of Control and Computer Engineering of Polytechnic of Turin. I have a Computer Science background. During my first year, I worked on modeling and forecasting financial time series but I'm slowly drifting to NLP with a particular focus on inspection and regularization of language models.

I am 25 and I spent the last 7 years in Turin, where I currently live. I love reading (Sci-Fi, please) and playing basketball, while circumstances led me to discover that I'm not so bad at cooking. I also like DIY and automating boring stuff.

Besides that, I am a passionate learner. I spend countless hours on lectures and tutorials about languages, frameworks, and technologies which I deem interesting.

**Research interests.** Sequence modeling and forecasting algorithms, inspection and understanding of deep NLP models, applied ML for quantitative trading

## Education

Politecnico di Torino, Italy

Ph.D. at Department of Control and Computer Engineering 2018 - ongoing

· Advisor: Elena Baralis

Politecnico di Torino, Italy

MD in Computer Engineering, Data Science track 2016 - 2018

• Grade: 110/110 cum Laude

Politecnico di TorinoTorino, ItalyBD IN COMPUTER ENGINEERING2013 - 2016

• Grade: 110/110

#### **Publications**

- **G. Attanasio**, E. Pastor, "PoliTeam @ AMI: Improving Sentence Embedding Similarity with Misogyny Lexicons for Automatic Misogyny Identification," Preprint, Nov. 2020
- **G. Attanasio**, L. Cagliero, and E. Baralis, "Leveraging the explainability of associative classifiers to support quantitative stock trading," in Proceedings of the Sixth International Workshop on Data Science for Macro-Modeling, New York, NY, USA, Jun. 2020, pp. 1–6, doi: 10.1145/3401832.3402679.
- **G. Attanasio** et al., "DSLE: A Smart Platform for Designing Data Science Competitions," in 2020 IEEE 44th Annual Computers, Software, and Applications Conference (COMPSAC), Jul. 2020, pp. 133–142, doi: 10.1109/COMPSAC48688.2020.00026.
- L. Cagliero, P. Garza, **G. Attanasio**, and E. Baralis, "Training ensembles of faceted classification models for quantitative stock trading," Computing, vol. 102, no. 5, pp. 1213–1225, May 2020, doi: 10.1007/s00607-019-00776-7.
- **G. Attanasio**, L. Cagliero, P. Garza, and E. Baralis, "Combining News Sentiment and Technical Analysis to Predict Stock Trend Reversal," in 2019 International Conference on Data Mining Workshops (ICDMW), Nov. 2019, pp. 514–521, doi: 10.1109/ICDMW.2019.00079.
- **G. Attanasio**, L. Cagliero, P. Garza, and E. Baralis, "Quantitative cryptocurrency trading: exploring the use of machine learning techniques," in Proceedings of the 5th Workshop on Data Science for Macro-

modeling with Financial and Economic Datasets, New York, NY, USA, Jun. 2019, pp. 1–6, doi: 10.1145/3336499.3338003.

#### (Before Ph.D.)

**G. Attanasio**, A. Cannavò, F. Cibrario, F. Lamberti, P. Montuschi, and G. Paravati, "HOT: Hold your own tools for AR-based constructive art," in 2017 IEEE Symposium on 3D User Interfaces (3DUI), Mar. 2017, pp. 256–257, doi: 10.1109/3DUI.2017.7893369.

## **Academic duties**

#### **TEACHING ASSISTANT**

- 2020 **Data science lab: processes and methods**, MD in Data Science and Engineering
- 2019 \* Data science lab: processes and methods, MD in Data Science and Engineering
- 2019 **Business Intelligence for Big Data**, MD in Industrial engineering and management
- 2018 **Databases**, BD in Computer Engineering

#### PEER REVIEWER

I reviewed at least one work submitted to the following venues:

- SAC 2021: the 36th ACM/SIGAPP Symposium On Applied Computing
- EDBT 2020: 23rd International Conference on Extending Database Technology
- IEEE ICDE 2020: 36th IEEE International Conference on Data Engineering
- ACM KDD 2020 26TH SIGKDD Conference On Knowledge Discovery And Data Mining
- DaWaK 2019: the 21st International Conference on Big Data Analytics and Knowledge Discovery

I reviewed at least one work submitted to the following journals:

• Future Generation Computer Systems, Elsevier

#### RESEARCH PROJECTS

I took part in a joint research project between my research group and the company KMaster (Telepass SpA). Along with my advisor and people from my research group, I designed and implemented an end-to-end machine learning and clustering-based pipeline to characterize driving behaviors and fleet management. The project is still ongoing.

## Work Experience \_\_\_\_\_

Kupata S.r.l.

Torino, Italy

FOUNDER, SHAREHOLDER

Nov. 2016 - ongoing

• Kupata's main goal is to streamline the Lost and Found process. It brings innovation with a solution that helps people in returning items in a simple, secure, and undisclosed way. The business involves a physical object, the Kupa, and a social community that encourages members to act in the right way.

<sup>\*</sup> The course rolled out the very first time in 2019, on the very first instance of the MD program in Data Science and Engineering @ PoliTO. The course was - and is still today - the first introduction to the Python programming language and the basics of Data Science/ML libraries for MD students. We worked hard to provide students with comprehensive exercises and solutions (10 laboratories, for a total of 60+ pages of lab exercises and 250+ pages of solutions).

Consoft Sistemi S.p.A. Torino, Italy

CURRICULAR INTERN Mar. 2016 - Jul. 2016

• I participated to the bootstrap phase of the Consoft's proprietary Knowledge Base platform. We built our solution upon Orange HRM, an open source PHP-based platform.

## Skills\_

I am familiar with *italicized* entries.

**Programming** C, C++, Python, Java, C#, JavaScript, PHP, Matlab, SQL

Framework Hadoop, Spark
Scripting Bash, Awk
DevOps AWS, Docker
Front-end Hugo, React, Dash

**Graphics** Inkscape, GIMP, *Blender, Unity 3D* 

**Languages** Italian, English, Spanish, French